hello thanks everyone for joining it's
March 29th 2023 we're in cohort 3 having
our first discussion on chapter five
so before we go into any questions or
look at the text
does anyone
want to just provide any general
reflection or thought on
chapter 5 or just the first half of the
book up till now
just unmute and go for it if you want to
okay let's look to chapter five
and then um
I'm sure people have many
thoughts as we get going
any general thoughts on five
or on this opening quotation about
plants and animals
well there are plants that move and the
the there does seem to be some
um thought that there are
interconnections between
um uh plants that they have a something
that while it is not a an animal uh
central nervous system they have they
that there there are
patterns within the um
architecture that have
similar functions and it's the timeline
over which they operate is much longer
I very much agree with that
here's my PhD advisor Deborah
and a paper from 1989
describing the plant's Behavior idea
and then
I believe a more closer to our area
is this 2017 paper
on plant predictive processing with
friston
so agreed the the this quote
it's a little bit of like time scale
dependent it's just kind of like a
it's a fun first pass but isn't that
interesting that it's like
it's actually not so Stark or the plants
that do respond like the Venus
flycatchers and everything
but
here in this chapter we're going to be
focused on the mammalian nervous system
and body
not the morphology of the nervous system
or like morphological development
okay
anyone please just raise your hand or or
write something otherwise let's just go
through chapter five and just look at
some
potentially interesting pieces
this is an interesting concept that not
every variable depends on every other
variable
and that's sparsity
and so there's sparsity in the brain
there are many connections but of the
space of the possible it's quite sparse
and similarly in statistical models
the sparser they are the easier they are
to fit
doesn't mean that it's going to be
better and a lot of modeling is about
finding the trade-off point between like
model complexity and model accuracy
because if you enable every Edge
it's going to be a really laborious
calculation
but if you restrict edges that are
actually important
you might have a very rapidly
fit model
however it might not reflect some of the
importance true causal relationships
amongst variables
so
that comes up in different ways
let us take a step back from the
technical material of chapter four
everyone
breathes aside
and turn our attention to the process
Theory's accompanying active inference
here they point to the difference
between a principal
free energy principle
which is that systems are described by
their Dynamics on free energy Landscapes
and that persistence is associated with
reduction of free energy
to the extent that agency is exerted
and a process theory about how any given
system may actually
Implement those kinds of Dynamics
so a principle cannot be falsified and
this is at the root of a lot of
questions and commentary around like the
falsification capacity for the free
energy principle and the simplest thing
as far as I've seen is neither can a
linear regression be falsified
it's just not within the space of being
confirmed or rejected or falsified by
anything at all
it's just a proposed model framework
as a principle
now any given linear regression
which is a specific hypothesis about how
that principle of linear regression or
the principle of the L2 Norm might be
implemented that given
linear model might be adequate or not
more adequate or totally inadequate or
however but it is more subject and
answerable to empirical data
so free energy principle
is not really in the space or the game
of falsification
or not
nor does it even engage with empirical
data directly
whereas proposed and manifest
models
are directly addressing empirical data
and empirical data speak to their
validity
so
none of the above chapters that we've
read
could be falsified by any observation in
the world
or they're just kind of
theoretical
whereas the models that are going to
start to be shown in in chapter five
are going to be structural and
computational hypotheses about models of
the nervous system and this they're more
addressable and answerable it's a real
data Jonathan
foreign
would it be reasonable to say that
um it may or may not be true that the
free energy principle is applicable to
certain Real World Systems but not that
the principle itself is wrong just that
it's not applicable
what does anyone want to add on that
Ali go for it
uh actually I came across a kind of a
situation that kind of contradicts some
of the claims of active inference or fep
uh about their scope of applicability
recently so
I'm not sure if you're familiar with
Stefan ferner's uh some of some of
Stephen Thurman's recent work but
basically uh he claims that uh complex
systems
um include a set of systems that are
only
non-markopian and non-ergotic systems
but on the other hand we had this notion
we have this requirement for any system
that is to be modeled in active
inference framework to be ergotic and
markovian systems
although in some recent literature
they've dropped this requirement for the
system to be ergotic but again I believe
uh a kind of local ergoticity needs to
be present in order for the system to be
to be modeled in fep or active inference
framework so uh
as as far as I know the scope of
applicability is
at least so far uh not strictly
uh defined or let's say it's not
something that can be
restricted in a definitional way but
there are degrees of applicabilities so
for instance
um in uh Dalton's Dalton's active
Edibles weak markup when a week blankets
paper
uh he has this notion of uh degrees of
blanketedness uh that helps us to
deliver distinguish between the systems
that have effective markup blankets and
the otherwise linear systems uh that
doesn't contain any kind of
um effective blanketedness uh so
briefly he claims that for higher
dimensional and complex systems we we
can apply these Bayesian mechanical
framework uh but
as for linear systems although
theoretically it is applicable for those
systems as well but it wouldn't result
in an interesting
uh an interesting uh Behavior because it
would basically be a kind of trivial
thing to apply uh these
Frameworks for a simple or simple in in
the sense of being linear systems
thank you ollie very um
very deep answer Michael
yeah I also read in some context that
this fep would explain how a system can
come into
the steady state
but it cannot explain how it comes out
why what triggers
um
the system to go out of that steady
state but this is constantly observed
right I mean we are not always in a
steady state but also jump into other
states
so I was I don't know whether this is an
implication exactly from what Ali you
said but I said that's why this free
energy principle could not be applied to
living systems even I think
yes thank you
well a lot of perspectives let's like
Focus that kind of question on on the
material of chapter five which is the
mammalian nervous system and behavior so
with copious citations and empirical
evidence
they're going to be talking about places
where the fep and active have been
applied
and so this is going to be much more
empirical and tangible and anatomical
than previous chapters
so whereas
the generative model proposed in chapter
four
and the high and the low road by which
that generative model is reached in
chapters three and two
were kind of in principle
here we're going to see a lot more about
what it looks like in practice
and that's going to mean that it's in
reference to a specific kind of system
like specific brain regions
and it's also going to mean that it's
answerable to empirical data
and that it's been published
according to professional communication
channels
signifying that it had unique
explanation or predictive power
so a lot of these are like fascinating
questions about the
hard and soft limits of applicability of
different methods
and we'll see in chapter five how that
plays out in practice
so again just write anything or raise
your hand if you'd like to to explore so
this chapter is not intended as the
final word on process theories
it's simply the interpretation that
seems most consistent with the currently
available evidence and
length constraints on the book
nors are aimed to endorse a specific
process Theory but to illustrate how the
ideas in the previous chapters may be
put to work
so if we were reading an anatomy
textbook or a psychology textbook it
would be like this is how it is
the elbow is connected to this and this
concept does this but the way that we're
going to be looking at the coming
examples
are like
representative of how models are
constructed that do
describe real systems of Interest
um
I'll
um bring your question
into here and and feel free to you can
continue this or add any more
information on what
type of generalist tools might help Coda
is certainly one generalist tool that
helps
and then there's many statistical
approaches that are more technical
so right now
we're going to be approaching this just
from the kind of like learning side but
the way that these models are
implemented
the code is generally available and so
this also provides some specific tools
and there may be other tools also but at
least tools that we use for learning
help us with Bayesian mechanics
in our engagement with it and then the
tools that actually Implement those
statistical models and then there may
also be other tools as well which would
be interesting to explore
um they describe the layout of the
chapter
which is going to be first focusing on
one of the most well-studied
neural systems which is the mammalian
cortex architecture
they're then going to expand into the
reflex arc
of the spinal cord and that will help us
look at the continuous time models of
perception and action
and then in section 5.4 talking about
decision making
all right
so in the end of chapter four
there were some representations that
looked like this
and this is showing two
um
related views
on a generative model on the left is a
hierarchical predictive processing model
where there are just as a graphical
convention
top-down predictions
and bottom-up sensory data and so this
is represented as kind of like a
skyscraper
just without reference to time the tilde
means Through Time
this in practice becomes unrolled
through these message passing
architectures and we talked a little bit
about that last week
here they're going to return to that
idea so
the skyscraper
the kinds of ways in which hierarchical
predictive processing architectures can
be
visualized or represented with a base
graph
those schemes
are going to be associated with
stereotype circuitry
and there's like
also coming from a long history of
taking pictures of the brain
an understanding of what the circuitry
is
in terms of synaptic connectivity and so
on
so they're going to describe a little
bit about this cortical column
and as an insect neuroscientist it's fun
to read all this because I just think
well this is one way it could be
but certainly all of these anatomical
details
they don't even necessarily have to be
that way for mammals but they definitely
don't have to be that way outside of
mammals
but connecting it to the reality of what
is empirically measured helps ground
Theory
and so figure 5.1 is going to be a side
by side
of the anatomy
of the cortical layers
has this mapping been done for the Clans
the synaptic connectivity of the um
whatever it is 302 neurons in the C
elegans
um for the most part has been completed
so snap connectivity does Maps do exist
oh I I mean the sort of the the
relationship between that map and and
the message passing
um that we we see here
um sort of the mapping between what
we're seeing on the left
um and what we're seeing in the middle
and the right
it would be awesome
as far as I know there is not an
explicit
um
nematode or even
um fruit fly or any other
um type of mapping but I think that's
very exciting work because there's like
a whole nematode simulation and there
are with brain and body and biomechanics
and um there are similar projects for
the drosophila
um Fly
so the um bulk of the work
of these authors Kristen at all and and
building on the legacy of SPM most of
the work has been done in human
neuroanatomy
and so not many people were considering
Beyond like the human neuroimaging case
until more recently
so
these six layers of the cortex are
defined histologically
so just from a tissue definition they
have some morphological differences and
they also have like some gene expression
and protein expression differences
and these edges
represent
physical structural connections amongst
different
um regions
it's juxtaposed and and these are kind
of the outputs inputs and outputs
with these the thalamus and so on
sending inputs into layer four
and then this kind of resonance
processing happening within a columnar
unit and then the outputs of this layer
5 cell going on to the decision making
areas that are going to be discussed in
Section 5 4.
and it's juxtaposed in kind of a visual
rhetorical Style
with
statistical
representations about what these
populations of cells might be doing
so that is helping
connect
the semantics of these variables
like this one is an error on this and
this one's a variance estimator on that
and this one's getting inputs about this
all those kinds of things that we want
to like talk about what a statistical
variable is doing
and mapping that onto empirically
observed patterns of neuroanatomy
now this is going to be kind of course
grained
this columnar unit which is repeated
thousands of times in the mammalian
cortex
is going to be abstracted
from the deep to the superficial
so this is that layer um
one two three four five six
superficial towards the surface of the
brain and then the deeper regions of the
cortex
so that
is going to be like one unit in this
figure 5.2
they have simplified what's happening
within a cortical region
to highlight what is happening amongst
cortical regions
and so there's processing happening
within a column
and also columns can serve as bottom up
and top down
for each other
so they're interacting laterally
from an anatomical perspective
however in this representation
the one on the right is like sending
top-down predictions to the one on the
left
and then bottom up prediction errors or
sensory inputs are coming up
to the one on the right
so this is showing that
predictive processing architectures can
be implemented laterally across cortical
columns
and this is at the root of a lot of
current computational modeling efforts
just
we'll leave it there and we'll return to
it
can I ask um
is that are they the Taylor series that
is that what that is the ascending
prediction or it's a I I was trying to
understand this Taylor series and it
seemed to be like a a way of
um creating a set of protections from a
function and you know so
whenever I looked at this I thought
that's the Taylor series
am I wrong in that
it it's a great insight and I think uh
as with with many of these things it's
like if you if you needed and want it to
be you can connect those locations so
for example
here's figure 4.3
and
um in the discrete time case we were
making explicit predictions about the
past present and future
in the continuous time case
rather than making explicit predictions
about the past present and future
we have the x hidden State variable
first derivative second derivative and
so on on X so that is like the Taylor
series coefficients
now
one could propose what if what this
cortical column was doing
was X
so it is getting sensory input this is
going to be raw sensory input coming in
or just from some other location and it
is going to be doing the role of
inference about X
and then
it is going to be constrained and
constraining
the rate of change in X so let's assign
the computational function of this
middle unit to like the derivative of x
and this one to the second derivative of
x
so this architecture could Implement
something like a Taylor series
approximation
you can make it that way in silico and
then you'll know or if you're talking
about real
brains
of course they're not actually doing a
Taylor series approximation on the
coefficients
but computationally they might be doing
something akin to it
so thank you Phillip yeah thank you so
figure 5.1
highlighted how layer 5 of the cortex
is going to be
projecting out
here's layer five
projecting out to some of these motor
and decision-making regions
so now we're going to treat the
descending prediction from that cortical
region
we're just going to have it up here
starting from the BET cells in layer 5
of the motor cortex so here's the BET
cells here's the motor cortex here's
like the brain
is sending a descending prediction
two in this case a cross-section of the
spinal cord
foreign
sensory data is incoming to the spinal
cord
through proprioception
afferent
means away
from the sensor efferent means to the
sensor
so proprioceptive data are coming away
from the sensor
and in
the actual
histology of the spinal cord
descending predictions about
proprioception
how one is expected to feel
and then the incoming proprioceptive
information
are being juxtaposed in this discrepancy
variable
subtracting the predictions from the
incoming data so just a simple
differencing
results in an error that says how much
muscle contraction would be required to
meet the prediction
so if the prediction is exactly what the
incoming data are
the discrepancy is zero
and no motor action is instigated
if it's non-zero motor auction would be
instigated
lower motor neurons then cause this
muscle contraction or relaxation
ensuring that the resulting
proprioceptive data match descending
predictions
so
we can have continuous this is a an
opportunity and and where continuous
time models have been studied a lot
because the incoming sensory data are
continuous
for example
um perceived uh weight
or just a different tactile Sensations
and then the outgoing
Behavior
can also be framed in a continuous
setting
like the elbow angle
and so this is like a simple statistical
architecture
that
situates motor action
as resolving the discrepancy
between predictions incoming
and data incoming
they move on to another region of the
mammalian nervous system
cortical layer 5 targets several other
structures
beyond the spinal cord
amongst these is the stratum
with these regions
and a lot is known about that region in
terms of gene expression and protein
expression and neurophysiology
so they're describing some of the
empirical
neurophysiology neuroanatomy
talking about figure 5.4 it's going to
come up
several Pages later though so just keep
that in mind
they're going to be talking
about policy selection
in the context of expected free energy
so here
we didn't need to talk about planning at
all
and continuous time models
are very Adept at describing these
situations where no explicit planning is
required but still adoptive action can
occur and we revisit that in chapter 8
on continuous time models
but now we're going to look at like
decision making kind of classical
psychologist type categorical decision
making
especially thinking about explicit
planning
and then they're going to talk about how
the architecture works but
we'll talk about that when we see it
dopamine tone is going to modulate the
balance of the two sides of the figure
and perturbations of dopamine are going
to have some behavioral and cognitive
consequences that are completely
compatible with this model
and just in general
the anatomy of figure 5 4 is endorsed by
evidence from both Clinical Pathology
and cellular morphology
so it's not the only map you can draw of
the territory
it isn't the territory itself
but
the map shown here is compatible with
the complexity of the territory
okay
so now
we're going to take those
um
just like they started the section off
on
outputs of cortical layer 5 are going to
Target other areas not just the spinal
cord
so
we're going to have
um
one
of those cortical outputs
sending into this brain region
there are going to be two Pathways
Illustrated so
one might be an effect or the other
and dopamine with this gamma variable
is um
modulating the balance between the two
so it's kind of like a rudder
the computational rule of dopamine is
acting like a Rudder with which one of
these Pathways is being
deployed
at a given time
here are what those two pathways are and
again this is going to be like a
behavioral computational
account
but it's also consistent with the
anatomy and with the clinical findings
What's called the indirect pathway
is one where the E vector
which is our habit
the affordances
are encoded in e
so different opportunities for Action
are enumerated in E and the numbers in
each of those cells refer to their prior
probability
so if there's um
up down left right there's going to be
four elements in e
and if it was 1 1 1 1 it means all
things are being equal
there's no prior
bias towards the direction to take
conversely in that up down left right
case what if it were a hundred one one
one
that would be equivalent to saying the
prior probability on going up is much
higher
and so in this indirect pathway the e
affordance vector
is basically being passed on through to
policy selection
and so policy posterior pi
is basically reflecting the policy prior
so
actions are being selected
proportional to how they have been
selected in the past
the distributions of actions being
selected in the indirect pathway
is being drawn from the same
distribution as habit
we can contrast that with what's called
by the neurophysiologist the direct
pathway
here we see that same kind of input
coming in
but rather than passing e on to Pi
we have G
so G
um is expected free energy
functional
so it's equation 2.6 and there's other
representations
and what G is doing
is taking in the E which is like not
shown but it does come into play so this
is not exhaustively showing every
variable just trying to only highlight
the differences between them really
G sharpens the action prior into
an action posterior
so that is updating the policy prior
into the posterior
through expected free energy
how does expected free energy
sharpen or modify the action prior into
the action posterior
it re-waits policies
according to their expected free energy
what is expected for energy
it's equation 2.6
so there's different decompositions
no one of which is simply like how it is
but policies are going to be updated
in becoming to their posterior
likelihood from which actions are
actually sampled from
and they're going to be sharpened or
updated according to
according to this Top Line
the pragmatic value and the information
gain of different policies
Michael
yeah one question so this posterior is
still an expected posterior
and we also have in the in the variation
free energy
another kind of posterior is that true
um every variable in Bayesian statistics
can be described that's that's going
undergoing updating
can be described of as having a prior
and then data comes in and then there's
the posterior
so here in particular we're talking
about the prior
and the posterior on action policies
but also we talk about priors and
posteriors for other kinds of variables
here the focus is how
um descending
information from the cerebral cortex
shapes policy selection
with the kind of neurophysiological
hypothesis not total expert that habit
is encoded
or represented
Within
this brain region
but cortical inputs
shift the balance towards a direct
pathway
so this is where we see like
deliberative decision making
because
we end up sharpening policies according
to their um
expected free energy so let's think
about like the famous marshmallow
example
um where a marshmallow is placed on a
table and someone can be taking it or
not
and they're told about what it is or
isn't or anything like that
so
if somebody had a habit of not taking
the marshmallow
then this pathway would lead them to not
take it if they had a habit of taking it
it would lead them to taking it
in this case in the direct pathway
policies would be evaluated
according to their epistemic and
pragmatic value
so in a model where pragmatic value or
sugar and there was a preference for
sugar
then policy selection would lead
to The Taking of the marshmallow
if pragmatic value in that model were
being defined as like Conformity to the
rules
then that Conformity would be realized
by not taking the marshmallow
so I know it's kind of like hard because
we're talking on one hand about actual
neurophysiology and behavioral patterns
but on the other hand about these
variables
but they're being juxtaposed here to to
show how it really does come into play
in empirical modeling yes Michael
but but all this um it's a planning this
is not based on an observation at that
moment right and how how does a surprise
uh come in there so surprise how can we
can can we also expect surprise and take
this into account in this um in this
expected free energy
so this is
um
showing just
a few distilled aspects of this graph
this is not the full model
observations are coming in
and so in that sense surprise being
about observations it could be
understood to be happening here it's
just not being like diagrammed
Yana what happens when there are more
options than a no nutrient stimulant yes
it um always
that's where we get into the um figure
9.1 not to look ahead but
depending on how the context is set up
for the experiment was it a two-choice
experiment was it a three-choice
experiment
and then that is the ethologists
challenge
to develop the as if View From the
Inside
the cognitive model of the subject
parameterized by their objective
behavior in this setting not the only
way to use these models
here
they uh
point to how certain dopamine signals
that famously incredibly famously
look like reward prediction errors
so one model of dopamine was like
dopamine is the reward molecule
and this Schultz 1997 paper was like
wait a minute
yes when more is received than expected
there's a dopamine Spike and that was
the pattern that people
um were associating with reward but if
it's the exact amount that was expected
there's no dopamine Spike
and if it's less than expected but still
a reward there's like another Spike
and so that was like wait a minute so
it's not just like a thermometer for
reward
maybe dopamine is doing something
like tracking prediction errors
so this is kind of like a proto-basian
brain proto-predictive coding
empirical find it
from the dopamine neurophysiology
that we now have like much much more
resolution on
and so active inference provides a
specific alternative explanation
to these phenomena
where we don't need to make all these
exceptions to a reward-based model well
it's dopamine is signaling reward but
then also it does that and also I don't
know why it does this
we can have a unified perspective
with active inference
on empirical data
here they're going to point to the idea
that
um specific hypotheses can be formed
yeah
another reason to use active inference
modeling for these kinds of cognitive uh
or I mean ultimately neurophysiological
settings
is that there can be non-invasive
measurement of precision parameters
and that's called computational
phenotyping and Ryan Smith and others
have done a lot of work on that
table 5.1
is going to list some of the important
neurotransmitters
and then even though neurotransmitters
do different things in different
settings and they're not saying
otherwise they're going to kind of
broadly associate it
with
a given computational function
so they interact and there's
neuropeptides and there's all this other
stuff happening
but broadly here are a bunch of lines of
evidence that support and understanding
of that neurotransmitter
associated with Precision acting on
these things
thanks for
um
sharing those Jonah
it reminds me of this um
2016 paper they gave ants
a choice between
um sugar water
and
um some dopamine drug
maybe morphine yeah morphine
and they like showed that they could
taper down the sugar
and the morphine and change a few
different things so that
um there was like a persistent
choice to go to the morphine
so I mean yes many many interesting
things to explore
but just to conclude on this part from
above computational phenotyping
basically means
probing a generative model construct
reducing our uncertainty about a
generative model
through peripheral measurements
so for example
pupil diameter
and eye movements
contain a lot of information on
somebody's arousal and attention
and so you don't need to have like an
implantable neurotech per se
you could use these non-invasive
measurements
and previously understood relationships
like between pupil size and
noradrenaline
so that you could actually reduce your
uncertainty about noradrenaline levels
just by looking at the pupil
they talk about heavy in plasticity
and different statistical models
5.6 continuous indiscrete hierarchies
this is also
um
a topic that's treated a lot more
extensively
in live stream 46.
active inference models do not
contradict folk psychology
but they highlight
a move from continuous representations
at low levels of a neural hierarchy
for example continuous sensory input
to categorical variables at higher
levels especially associated with
semantics identification and decision
making
so
we're able to hold categorical beliefs
and interface with continuously varying
sensory receptors and effectors
like muscle length or visual features
that is just kind of brought up in these
two short paragraphs in 5.6
and then in figure eight
point six this is an example of what the
generative model looks like
so at the higher level there's a missing
line here but at the higher level we
have a discrete time generative model
partially observable Markov decision
process pomdp how do we know because it
has the Tau minus one Tau Tau plus one
so this is making explicit predictions
about the past present and future and in
this case it's also making categorical
inferences
so is it a or b or oh it's a and b
because those letters are also used here
but is it raining or is it sunny
and we're just going to have a
categorical difference between those two
and have that estimate happening past
present future
but then at each time step
there's a continuous time model
and so here we can recognize the
continuous time model because we see
that x x Prime X double Prime
and so we have like this big rake
Big E pointing down
and then here's a smaller one
so it's kind of like figure 4.3
here's discrete time Model E pointing
down
continuous time Model E pointing down
and then those are going to be
grafted together
so we have a higher order slower
discrete time model
and then a faster continuous time model
so this could reflect and this is what
they discuss in live stream 46.
with um Alex Kiefer Ryan Smith and
Maxwell ramstead
they discuss how
decision making like should I go to the
baker or to the barber
is occurring in a discrete like way
in this decision making
model
but then the implementation of the
decision-making model is happening in a
continuous type model
which they call motor active inference
Mai
um
so the good thing about
figure 4.3
is these are enormously flexible methods
this is not like the one and only way an
active inference model looks it's really
almost bewilderingly the opposite of
that
this isn't like the zoo of what's out
there
these are showing some of the structural
possibilities for cognitive modeling
and there are many possibilities and
there's many ways to model the same
phenomena
um Jana asked how is the continuous
hierarchy applied
well
you can add more information but one can
make a hierarchical model where like the
higher level was continuous and the
output of a given like the Y here we
could graft another continuous time
model right here
so these are like our our Lego kits
these are a few Lego constructions that
people have made
that typify
minimal skeletons of cognitive models
but what's really important is that the
cognitive models that we build
are going to have tractable ways to do
inference on them
because of message passing
so then they closed the chapter with
this summary visualization so it's the
three systems that we learned about in
the chapter
which is dot cortical column
the balance between the indirect and the
direct Pathways of policy selection in
the basal ganglia midbrain
and the action
selection in that continuous time model
happening via the spinal cord
discrepancy detection
and so this is kind of
reflective and compatible with the
actual anatomical connectivity
of the body so it's not like proposing a
telepathic link between some cell in the
brain and like the motor
uh unit in the arm
so it's compatible with the constraints
that exist in the body
it explains and predicts different
phenomena
that are observed
and those explanations come not from
just trivial well if two things that are
touching are influenced then one
influences the other but rather with
actually these statistical models
that even help us understand the
progression or different kinds of
interventions in different conditions
which is where these models have been
used most
so that's the end of that
chapter five
but they kind of close
with um
a reminder that like Neuroscience is a
work in progress
and
um there are so many
open
questions
from the super cellular level
like where are the glia where's the
immuno aspect
to different kinds of everything
they're just picking three examples
that have been studied in previous
papers by these authors
and showing how alone
and in combination we can use these
kinds of models
so Jana asked
so this is how sensory experiences can
be modeled
broadly
this
could help us make sense of sensory
experience this isn't like the one and
only way to model sensory experience
this is like one circuit board
statistical model
that can
help with understanding how incoming
proprioception
results in outgoing action
so it can be used in service of
understanding sensory experience
but this is not the the final model on
sensory experience I hope that that's
clear
there can be other compositions yes
so
any other
thoughts or comments on this first pass
through five Michael
yeah but in this figure 5.5 that you
just showed uh is still the observation
the sensation is actually missing there
right
so we have action but not the
observation
um here the input Y is the
proprioceptive input
but other kinds like visual input is not
shown here
but that is that speaks to the
composability of these models
is like we could have an auditory stream
and a visual stream and a proprioceptive
stream
and we can do model comparison and we
can develop models that use any mixtures
of those
and on given computational hardware for
a given data set for a given setting for
a given client one of those models might
be more useful than the other for you
okay thank you yeah it's a fun chapter
and I it's definitely a context switch
because chapter four just goes so hard
with the technical details
and then 5.3 is really like about our
bodies
but in that contrast there's been a lot
of great discussion so
um next week we'll return for the second
discussion on five
please feel free to ask your questions
in the meanwhile so thank you everybody
see you next time